Finding Aid for Latina/o Studies Program (University of Michigan) records, 1984-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Latina/o Studies Program (University of Michigan) records 1984-2007, 1986-2000
University of Michigan. Latina/o Studies Program.
3.5 linear feet
2014114 Bimu 2
Housed within the Program in American Culture and originally developed in response to student, faculty, and staff activism at the University, the Latina/o Studies Program at the University of Michigan was founded in the fall of 1984. The Latina/o Studies Program provides an interdisciplinary pan-Latina/o approach to the study of Latina/o history, politics, cultures, social relations, and artistic expression in the United States. The records in this collection date from 1984-2007, with the majority of the records from the period 1986-2000, and document the administrative, teaching, research, and public programs functions of the Latina/o Studies Program.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Accessions received from the Latina/o Studies Program (Donor No. 10290 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Latina/o Studies Program records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational record.
The Latino Studies record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Box 4
Student Academic Records -- Box 4
The Latina/o Studies Program at the University of Michigan forms a curricular unit within the University's Program in American Culture, created in 1952. As part of its commitment towards studying and teaching the complexity and diversity of cultural experiences in the United States, in response to growing local and national interest in the history and culture of Hispanic peoples, and as a result of student activism at the University of Michigan, the Program in American Culture initiated offerings in Latina/Latino studies in 1984.
The Latina/o studies movement in the United States developed as an academic field in the late 1960s and early 1970s in the wake of decades' long fight by minorities for civil rights in the United States. The discipline's early years witnessed the growth of Chicano studies programs in the West and Southwest and Puerto Rican studies in New York.1 Throughout the 1970s the University of Michigan administration expressed an interest in recruitment of Chicano students and faculty, and worked towards a goal of developing curriculum for and about Chicanos. Although Latina/o studies grew from somewhat nationalistic perspectives in its early years, the field that matured in the 1980s as Latina/o studies was broader and more inclusive. In the early 1980s, the University of Michigan, through its "University Courses," as well as the Program in American Culture, developed curriculum to teach courses in the field of Hispanic-American studies. However, until the inception of the Latino Studies Program in 1984 the University lacked a curricular unit devoted exclusively to Latina/o studies.
The creation of an academic unit focused on Latina/o studies was due in large part to the activism of Latina/o students, staff, and faculty on the University of Michigan campus. In January 1984, a coalition of Latino students met with interested College of Literature, Science, and the Arts faculty and administrators to propose a new unit that to "focus on the Hispanic experience in the United States, emphasizing their history, culture and contributions..." Representatives from the campus' Hispanic student, faculty, and staff organizations then lobbied for an academic unit that would focus on the Latina/o experience in the United States. In the winter of 1984, the College Executive Committee discussed the issue of curriculum development in Hispanic-American studies and formed a committee, the Hispanic-American Studies Program Committee (later renamed the Latino Studies Program Committee) to explore the issue and provide recommendations on the development of a curriculum in Latino Studies. In a letter to "All Hispanic Students at Michigan and Friends," Visiting Professor and Acting Director of the Latino Studies Program John Chávez wrote that the new program was "the first of its kind at Michigan and indicates that the University is now recognizing the full significance of Hispanics, the most rapidly growing ethnic group in the nation."2
Over the course of its first year, the Latino Studies Program offered courses such as "The 'Hispanic' Southwest," "Hispanic America," "Historical Approaches/Topics in U.S. and Latin American History," "Introduction to Latino Studies," and "Mexican-American Literature." Although the majority of the unit's classes were initially offered through the American Culture Program, in ensuing years courses were offered in partnership with a academic units from across the campus. Indeed, the Latina/o studies program at the University of Michigan reflects the diversification of the field begun in the 1980s and developed through the 1990s
Today, the Latina/o Studies Program at the University of Michigan offers an interdisciplinary and pan-Latina/o approach for graduate and undergraduate students to the study of Latina/o history, politics, cultures, social relations, and artistic expression in the United States, as well as offering a transnational perspective. Central to the philosophy of the program is the belief that no one group of Latina/os can be studied in isolation, and the best understanding of the history and future of Latina/os in the United States will come from comparative study. Among the departments that have contributed faculty and resources to the Latina/o Studies Program are: Anthropology, English, History, Romance Languages and Literatures, Film Studies, Sociology, the School of Music, and Women's Studies. Former Program Director Frances R. Aparicio argues that the Latina/o Studies Program's location within the Program in American Culture has fostered "multiracial, interdisciplinary, and cultural interaction" that has been "healthy for the intellectual development of both professors and students of every racial and ethnic group."3 And, that the Latina/o Studies program has had a positive effect on the campus by "destabliz[ing] disciplinary, linguistic, and ethnic boundaries of knowledge production."4
The Latina/o Studies Program regularly invites artists, writers, poets, performers, and visiting scholars to campus for short visits, minicourses, and performances. Visiting scholars such as Sandra Cisneros, Judith Ortiz Cofer, and Norma Cantú, have also offered longer in-residence courses. Among the performers and filmmakers that have visited the University of Michigan under the auspices of the Latina/o Studies Program are Carmelita Tropicana, Coco Fusco, Frances Negrón, Lourdes Portillo, Dolissa Medina, and others. In addition to academic work, the Latina/o Studies Program encourages student participation in community service organizations that service local Latino/a communities in southeast Michigan.
Undergraduate students in Latina/o Studies have the option of doing either a minor or concentration in the Program. The minor in Latina/o Studies, established in 2000, requires that students complete eighteen credit hours, including the American Culture course "Introduction to Latino Studies," that introduces them to the variety of disciplinary approaches to the study of Latina/os in the United States, as well as the field's central research questions and theory. The concentration program in Latina/o Studies, founded in 1984, is similar to the minor, but requires the completion of 30 credit units.
Graduate students interested in Latina/o Studies must first apply to the Graduate Program in American Culture, prior to enrolling in the Latina/o Studies Program. The graduate program shares with the undergraduate curriculum a strong interdisciplinary approach to Latina/o Studies in the United States that also includes consideration of feminism, queer theory, transnational media studies, critical race theory, and border studies and theory. In addition to theory, the Latina/o Studies Program also incorporates humanities and social sciences including history, literature, film studies, and ethnomusicology. The graduate program is a member of the Midwest Latino/a Studies Consortium, which fosters collaboration amongst students, faculty, and staff in the Midwest. The Latina/o Studies Program also offers a Graduate Certificate to University of Michigan graduate students enrolled in departments other than American Culture. The certificate program is a 15-credit hour course of study designed to provide students with an in-depth understanding of the field.
Program Names
1984-1991 Latino Studies Program
1992-1996 Latina/Latino Studies Program
1997 – Present Latina/o Studies Program
Program Directors
1984-1986 John R. Chávez (Interim Director)
1986-1990 Silvia Pedraza (Acting Director)
1991 (Acting Director) Walter Mignolo
1991-1992 Frances Aparicio and Ruth Behar (Acting Directors)
1992-1994 Margarita de la Vega-Hurtado (Acting Director)
1994-1996 Frances Aparicio
1997-1999 Tomás Almaguer
2000-2002 Ivette Perfecto (Acting Director)
2002- 2003 Tomás Almaguer
2004-2006 Maria Montoya
2007 Catherine Benamou
2008 Silvia Pedraza (Interim Director)
Fall 2008 – 2011 Maria Cotera
2011- Lawrence M. La Fountain-Stokes
1. Juan Poblete, Ed., Critical Latin American and Latino Studies (Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2003), 4.
2. John Chávez, Visiting Assistant Professor, Latino Studies and Hector Delgado, Teaching Assistant, Latino Studies to "All Hispanic Students at Michigan and Friends," 1 November 1984, Folder: Latina/o Studies, History 1980-1986, Box 4, Program in American Culture (University of Michigan), Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.
3. Frances R. Aparicio, interviewed by Juan Zevallos Aguilar and quoted in "Latino Cultural Studies," in Juan Poblete, Ed., Critical Latin American and Latino Studies (Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2003), 10.
4. Ibid.
The Latina/o Studies Program records document the administrative, teaching, research, and public programs functions of the Latino Studies Program. The records in this collection measure 2.5 linear feet, and date from 1984 to 2007, with the majority of the records from the period 1986 to 2000. They are primarily comprised of correspondence, event flyers, meeting minutes, program planning materials, course descriptions and schedules, syllabi, event flyers and promotional materials, faculty search documents, information on visiting professors, and materials from Latina/o staff, faculty, and student organizations at the University of Michigan. The records are organized into five series: Administrative Files, Curriculum, Events and Programs, Faculty, and Latina/o Organizations.
Subjects:
Hispanic Americans--Education.; Hispanic Americans--History.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan.; Hispanic Americans--Study and teaching (Higher); Multiculturalism--Study and teaching (Higher); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Latina/o Studies Program.; University of Michigan. Program in American Culture.
- Administrative Files 1984-2007
  The Administrative Files series, 1984-2007 (1.25 linear ft.), includes meeting minutes and notes from Latina/o Studies Advisory Committee and Faculty meetings, proposals and planning materials for the undergraduate concentration program, files from Latina/o Studies Program Directors, funding proposals, budget materials, departmental brochures, and program planning materials and proposals that document the evolution of the Program from its origins in 1984.
  - Office Files
    - Support Positions 1992 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee Agendas, Minutes, and Notes
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
    - 1997 (Box 1)
    - 1998 (Box 1)
    - 2001 (Box 1)
    - 2003 (Box 1)
    - 2004 (Box 1)
    - 2005 (Box 1)
    - 2007 (Box 1)
  - Concentration Program
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - 2001 (Box 1)
  - Degree Audit
    - 2005 (Box 1)
  - Directors' Files
    - General Files
      - Acting Director Announcement 1993 (Box 1)
      - General Files 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      - Position Description Undated (Box 1)
    - Individual Files
      - Almaguer, Tomas 1993-2004 (Box 4)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2034 ]
      - Aparicio, Frances 1990-1991 (Box 4)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2021 ]
      - Mignolo, Walter 1990 (Box 4)
        [RP Restricted until July 1 2020 ]
      - Pedraza-Bailey, Silvia 1986-1989 (Box 4)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2019 ]
  - Ethnic Studies Program
    - Ethnic Studies Initiative 1994 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meetings
    - Minutes 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Finance and Budget
    - Budget Reports 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Budget 1995 (Box 1)
    - Funding Proposals undated
      - 1991 (Box 1)
      - 1992 (Box 1)
      - 1993 (Box 1)
      - 1994 (Box 1)
      - 1995 (Box 1)
      - 1996 (Box 1)
      - 1997 (Box 1)
      - 1998 (Box 1)
      - 2001 (Box 1)
      - 2005 (Box 1)
      - 2007 (Box 1)
    - Student Organization Funding Requests 1993-1998 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Program
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 2001 (Box 1)
  - Minor Program
    - 2004 (Box 1)
  - Program Planning
    - Annual Reports 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Program Descriptions 1988, 1993 & Undated (Box 1)
    - Program Planning Reports and Notes
      - 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1987 (Box 1)
      - 1988 (Box 1)
      - 1997 (Box 1)
      - 2000 (Box 1)
      - 2001 (Box 1)
  - Promotional Materials and Publications
    - Brochures and Promotional Pieces, 1993and Undated (Box 1)
    - Newsletter 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Program Booklet Undated (Box 1)
    - Website Text 2004 (Box 1)
  - Resources
    - Bibliography 1994 & Undated (Box 1)
    - Latina/o Campus Resources Undated (Box 1)
  - Students
    - Student Grievance 1987 (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2062 ]
- Curriculum 1984-2002
  Materials in the Curriculum series, 1984-2002 (.50 linear ft.), document the teaching work of the Latina/o Studies program and include course offerings by year, syllabi, course proposals, syllabi, and information on service learning.
  - Course Offerings
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
    - 1997 (Box 1)
    - 1998 (Box 1)
    - 1999 (Box 1)
    - 2001 (Box 1)
    - 2002 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Proposals
    - 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Service Learning
    - 1986-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Syllabi
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999 (Box 2)
    - 2000 (Box 2)
    - 2001 (Box 2)
  - Theme Semester
    - 1992-1995 (Box 2)
- Events and Programs 1986-2007
  The Events and Programs series, 1986-2007 (.25 linear ft.), includes flyers, program materials, and correspondence relating to special events, program, workshops, performances, screenings, talks, and lectures sponsored or co-sponsored by the Latina/o Studies Program.
  - Conferences, Symposia, & Workshops
    - Chicano History Week
      - 1987 (Box 2)
      - 1996 (Box 2)
    - National Association for Chicano/a Studies Conference 1995 (Box 2)
    - King Symposium 2005 (Box 2)
    - Latino Studies in the Midwest 2004 (Box 2)
    - Nuestro Ambiente 2002 (Box 2)
    - Natures Past: Comparative Perspectives on Environmental Change 2003 (Box 2)
    - Puerto Rican Week 1986 & 1994 (Box 2)
    - Rhythms of Culture: Dancing to Las Americas 1997 (Box 2)
    - SCOR Conference 2001 (Box 2)
    - Sin Vergüenza! (Shameless): An Interdisciplinary Conference on Latino/a Sexuality 2000 (Box 2)
  - Lectures and Talks
    - Speakers
      - Aponte-Parés, Luis 1996 (Box 2)
      - Caro, Manuel 1995 (Box 2)
      - Cervantes, Lorna Dee 1993 (Box 2)
      - Chavez, Ernesto 1996 (Box 2)
      - Cisneros, Sandra 1993 & 2006 (Box 2)
      - Espada, Martín 1997 (Box 2)
      - López, Ian Haney 1997 (Box 2)
      - Martínez, Elizabeth (Betita) Undated (Box 2)
      - Rodrí guez, Luis 1996 (Box 2)
    - Lecture Flyers, including Brown Bags
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1988 (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - 1992 (Box 2)
      - 1993 (Box 2)
      - 1994 (Box 2)
      - 1995 (Box 2)
      - 1996 (Box 2)
      - 1997 (Box 2)
      - 1999 (Box 2)
      - 2001 (Box 2)
      - 2004 (Box 2)
      - 2006 (Box 2)
  - Performances, Exhibits, & Screenings
    - Assorted Flyers
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1997-2007 (Box 2)
    - Gleaton, Tony Undated (Box 2)
    - Prades, Danis Pérez Undated (Box 2)
  - Special Events and Celebrations
    - Anzaldúa Memorial 2004 (Box 2)
    - Assorted Flyers 1986-2007 (Box 2)
    - Latina Retreat 1994 (Box 2)
    - Town Hall 1991-2001 (Box 2)
- Faculty 1985-2007
  The records in the Faculty series, 1985-2007 (.25 linear ft.), document the growth of the Latina/o Studies Program since its inception in 1984. The materials in this series include proposals for visiting professorships, records from visiting faculty, cluster hire requests and reports, job descriptions, candidate applications, and evaluations of potential faculty members and program directors.
  - Award Nominations
    - 1996 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2026 ]
  - Hiring
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 4)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 4)
    - 1993 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2023 ]
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
    - 1999 (Box 2)
    - 2000 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2030 ]
    - 2001 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2031 ]
    - 2002 (Box 2)
    - 2003 (Box 2)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Visiting Professors
    - General 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Burciaga, José Antonio 1995 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
    - Cantú, Norma 1996 (Box 4)
    - Hernández Cruz, Victor 1994 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2024 ]
    - Gutierrez, David G. 1998 (Box 4)
    - Levins Morales, Aurora 1994 (Box 4)
    - Limón, José F. 1987 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2017 ]
    - Montejano, David 1999 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2029 ]
    - Ortiz Cofer, Judith 1991 (Box 4)
    - Pantojas-García, Emilio 1995 (Box 4)
    - Ruiz, Vicki L. 2005 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2035 ]
    - Samora, Julian 1987 (Box 4)
    - Tropicana, Carmelita 1996 (Box 4)
    - Vargas, George 2003 (Box 4)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2033 ]
- Latina/o Organizations 1986-2007
  The Latina/o Organizations series, 1986-2007 (.25 linear ft.), documents some of the faculty, staff, and student organizations interested and active in Latina/o issues, politics, and scholarship at the University of Michigan and in the greater Midwest. The series primarily includes promotional materials, such as brochures, for these organizations, workshop schedules, and event flyers.
  - Alianza 1995 (Box 3)
  - ALMA 2007 (Box 3)
  - Chicano Graduate Students 1987 (Box 3)
  - Delta Tau Lambda 1994 (Box 3)
  - Fuerza 1996 (Box 3)
  - Latino Faculty and Staff Association 2001-2007 (Box 3)
  - La Voz 1997 (Box 3)
  - Lucha Movement 1997 (Box 3)
  - Midwest Consortium for Latino Research 1994-1998, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Puerto Rican Association 1987-1995 (Box 3)
  - Socially Active Student Association
    - 1986 (Box 3)
    - 1992 (Box 3)
Related material
Researchers should note that related material on the Latina/o Studies Program can be found in the Program in American Culture (University of Michigan) records, the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) records, and the Vice Provost for Academic and Multicultural Affairs (University of Michigan) records, also located at the Bentley Historical Library. These collections include the Chicano Studies Deans' files (1972-1974), files for Hispanic American Studies (1985-1988), general files on the Latino Studies Program (1987-1992), Latino Studies Advisory Committee Minutes and Correspondence (1984-1992), Director Search (1990-1992), faculty searches (1985-1990), Concentration Planning documents (1987-1990), courses (1987-1993), teaching assignments (1978-1992), visiting professors (1991-1994), newsletters (1985-1986), and the 1989/1990 External Review of the Latino Studies Program.
Researchers looking for additional information on Latina/os in the state of Michigan may also wish to consult the Bentley Historical Library's "Latinos in Michigan" online subject guide which lists all collections held at the Bentley that document Latinos in Michigan. The subject guide is located at: http://bentley.umich.edu/research/guides/latino/index.php.